This domain will cover two prevalent programming
concepts: decisions and loops. We will learn quite
a bit about conditions and how they control the
flow of a program. As we cover these concepts,
you will also learn about some unique syntax
needs in Python compared to other programming
languages such as C#, Java, and JavaScript. The
first condition we will cover revolves around an
if statement. An if statement takes action if
a condition is true. A real-life example for
me on many weekends is if it’s sunny outside, I
will play golf. Take a look at this 211-if code
example. We are setting up conditions for actions
based on a score achieved in a game. The score
variable is on line 1. The if statement starts on
line 3. We have the keyword if, followed by the
condition, the score is greater than 10000, and
then a colon indicates the condition's end. The
following line, line 4, is the action to perform
if the condition is true, which, for this example,
is a print statement with a message. Before we run
this code, there is a fundamental concept we need
to understand for Python syntax: indentation.
Many programming languages, with if and similar
statements, have the actions to take for a
condition inside curly brackets. Python does not
use curly brackets in this manner. Rather, Python
uses indents to indicate what code should run as
part of a condition, loop, or function. Line 4
is indented four spaces from line 3. To emphasize
indenting code, I have a print statement on line
5 that is not indented and tells the player thank
you for playing. In analyzing the code as it
is now, the if statement is true because the
score is over 10000, so the statement on line
4 should print. Line 5 should print regardless
because it is not indented and thus not part of
the if statement. I will run this code, and both
statements print as expected. What if we change
the code on line 1 to lower the score to a number
under 10000? I will change the score to 8000. How
many print statements do you think will print when
we run this code? If the if condition is false,
this statement should not print. However, the
statement on line 5 should be printed because it
is not indented and thus not part of the condition
in the if statement on line 3. Having rerun the
code, that is what happened. The print statement
on line 4 did not print because the condition
on line 3 is false. But the print statement on
line 5 did print because it is not part of the
if statement as it is not indented. Many aspects
of an app are based on conditions, and thus, we
must understand conditional statements such as
the if statement so that, based on a situation,
we can control what happens next within our code.